<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE fb-non-chapter PUBLIC "-//ES//DTD book DTD version 5.5.0//EN//XML" "book550.dtd" [<!ENTITY uauther-001-9780702070280 SYSTEM "uauther-001-9780702070280" NDATA IMAGE>]><fb-non-chapter docsubtype="htu" id="htu00037" version="5.5" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/bk/dtd" xmlns:ce="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/common/dtd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><info><ce:pii>B978-0-7020-7028-0.00037-8</ce:pii><ce:doi>10.1016/B978-0-7020-7028-0.00037-8</ce:doi><ce:isbn>978-0-7020-7028-0</ce:isbn><ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2018">Elsevier Ltd</ce:copyright></info><ce:title id="tit0010">Sir Stanley Davidson (1894–1981)</ce:title><ce:para id="p0010"><ce:display><ce:figure id="f0010"><ce:alt-text id="atte0010" role="short">Unlabelled image</ce:alt-text><ce:link id="ln0010" locator="uauther-001-9780702070280" xlink:href="pii:B9780702070280000378/uauther-001-9780702070280" xlink:role="http://data.elsevier.com/vocabulary/ElsevierContentTypes/23.4" xlink:type="simple"/></ce:figure></ce:display></ce:para><ce:para id="p0015">This famous textbook was the brainchild of one of the great Professors of Medicine of the 20th century. Stanley Davidson was born in Sri Lanka and began his medical undergraduate training at Trinity College, Cambridge; this was interrupted by World War I and later resumed in Edinburgh. He was seriously wounded in battle, and the carnage and shocking waste of young life that he encountered at that time had a profound effect on his subsequent attitudes and values.</ce:para><ce:para id="p0020">In 1930 Stanley Davidson was appointed Professor of Medicine at the University of Aberdeen, one of the first full-time Chairs of Medicine anywhere and the first in Scotland. In 1938 he took up the Chair of Medicine at Edinburgh and was to remain in this post until retirement in 1959. He was a renowned educator and a particularly gifted teacher at the bedside, where he taught that everything had to be questioned and explained. He himself gave most of the systematic lectures in Medicine, which were made available as typewritten notes that emphasised the essentials and far surpassed any textbook available at the time.</ce:para><ce:para id="p0025"><ce:italic>Principles and Practice of Medicine</ce:italic> was conceived in the late 1940s with its origins in those lecture notes. The first edition, published in 1952, was a masterpiece of clarity and uniformity of style. It was of modest size and price, but sufficiently comprehensive and up to date to provide students with the main elements of sound medical practice. Although the format and presentation have seen many changes in 22 subsequent editions, Sir Stanley's original vision and objectives remain. More than half a century after its first publication, his book continues to inform and educate students, doctors and health professionals all over the world.</ce:para></fb-non-chapter>