<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE introduction PUBLIC "-//ES//DTD book DTD version 5.5.0//EN//XML" "book550.dtd" [<!ENTITY icon01-9780702070280 SYSTEM "icon01-9780702070280" NDATA IMAGE><!ENTITY icon02-9780702070280 SYSTEM "icon02-9780702070280" NDATA IMAGE><!ENTITY icon03-9780702070280 SYSTEM "icon03-9780702070280" NDATA IMAGE><!ENTITY icon04-9780702070280 SYSTEM "icon04-9780702070280" NDATA IMAGE><!ENTITY icon05-9780702070280 SYSTEM "icon05-9780702070280" NDATA IMAGE><!ENTITY icon06-9780702070280 SYSTEM "icon06-9780702070280" NDATA IMAGE>]><introduction docsubtype="itr" id="itr00043" version="5.5" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/bk/dtd" xmlns:ce="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/common/dtd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><info><ce:pii>B978-0-7020-7028-0.00043-3</ce:pii><ce:doi>10.1016/B978-0-7020-7028-0.00043-3</ce:doi><ce:isbn>978-0-7020-7028-0</ce:isbn><ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2018">Elsevier Ltd</ce:copyright></info><ce:title id="tit0010">Introduction</ce:title><ce:sections><ce:para id="p0010">The opening six chapters of the book, making up Part 1 on ‘Fundamentals of Medicine’, provide an account of the principles of genetics, immunology, infectious diseases and population health, along with a discussion of the core principles behind clinical decision-making and good prescribing. Subsequent chapters in Part 2, ‘Emergency and Critical Care Medicine’, discuss medical emergencies in poisoning, envenomation and environmental medicine, while a new chapter explores common presentations in acute medicine, as well as the recognition and management of the critically ill. The third part, ‘Clinical Medicine’, is devoted to the major medical specialties. Each chapter has been written by experts in the field to provide the level of detail expected of trainees in their discipline. To maintain the book's virtue of being concise, care has been taken to avoid unnecessary duplication between chapters.</ce:para><ce:para id="p0015">The system-based chapters in Part 3 follow a standard format, beginning with an overview of the relevant aspects of clinical examination, followed by an account of functional anatomy, physiology and investigations, then the common presentations of disease, and details of the individual diseases and treatments relevant to that system. In chapters that describe the immunological, cellular and molecular basis of disease, this problem-based approach brings the close links between modern medical science and clinical practice into sharp focus.</ce:para><ce:para id="p0020">The methods used to present information are described below.</ce:para><ce:section id="s0010"><ce:section-title id="st0010">Clinical examination overviews</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0025">The value of good clinical skills is highlighted by a two-page overview of the important elements of the clinical examination at the beginning of most chapters. The left-hand page includes a mannikin to illustrate key steps in examination of the relevant system, beginning with simple observations and progressing in a logical sequence around the body. The right-hand page expands on selected themes and includes tips on examination technique and interpretation of physical signs. These overviews are intended to act as an aide-mémoire and not as a replacement for a detailed text on clinical examination, as provided in our sister title, <ce:italic>Macleod's Clinical Examination.</ce:italic></ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="s0015"><ce:section-title id="st0015">Presenting problems</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0030">Medical students and junior doctors must not only assimilate a great many facts about various disorders but also develop an analytical approach to formulating a differential diagnosis and a plan of investigation for patients who present with particular symptoms or signs. In <ce:italic>Davidson</ce:italic>'s this is addressed by incorporating a ‘Presenting Problems’ section into all relevant chapters. Nearly 250 presentations are included, which represent the most common reasons for referral to each medical specialty.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="s0020"><ce:section-title id="st0020">Boxes</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0035">Boxes are a popular way of presenting information and are particularly useful for revision. They are classified by the type of information they contain, using specific symbols.</ce:para><ce:section id="s0025"><ce:section id="s0030"><ce:section id="s0035"><ce:section-title id="st0025"><ce:inline-figure baseline="0.0"><ce:link id="ln0010" locator="icon01-9780702070280" xlink:href="pii:B9780702070280000433/icon01-9780702070280" xlink:role="http://data.elsevier.com/vocabulary/ElsevierContentTypes/23.4" xlink:type="simple"/><ce:alt-text id="atte0010" role="short">Image 1</ce:alt-text></ce:inline-figure> General Information</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0040">These include causes, clinical features, investigations, treatments and other useful information.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="s0040"><ce:section-title id="st0030"><ce:inline-figure baseline="0.0"><ce:link id="ln0015" locator="icon03-9780702070280" xlink:href="pii:B9780702070280000433/icon03-9780702070280" xlink:role="http://data.elsevier.com/vocabulary/ElsevierContentTypes/23.4" xlink:type="simple"/><ce:alt-text id="atte0015" role="short">Image 2</ce:alt-text></ce:inline-figure> Practice Point</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0045">There are many practical skills that students and doctors must master. These vary from inserting a nasogastric tube to reading an ECG or X-ray, or interpreting investigations such as arterial blood gases or thyroid function tests. ‘Practice Point’ boxes provide straightforward guidance on how these and many other skills can be acquired and applied.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="s0045"><ce:section-title id="st0035"><ce:inline-figure baseline="0.0"><ce:link id="ln0020" locator="icon06-9780702070280" xlink:href="pii:B9780702070280000433/icon06-9780702070280" xlink:role="http://data.elsevier.com/vocabulary/ElsevierContentTypes/23.4" xlink:type="simple"/><ce:alt-text id="atte0020" role="short">Image 3</ce:alt-text></ce:inline-figure> Emergency</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0050">These boxes describe the management of many of the most common emergencies in medicine.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="s0050"><ce:section-title id="st0040"><ce:inline-figure baseline="0.0"><ce:link id="ln0025" locator="icon02-9780702070280" xlink:href="pii:B9780702070280000433/icon02-9780702070280" xlink:role="http://data.elsevier.com/vocabulary/ElsevierContentTypes/23.4" xlink:type="simple"/><ce:alt-text id="atte0025" role="short">Image 4</ce:alt-text></ce:inline-figure> In Old Age</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0055">In many countries, older people comprise 20% of the population and are the chief users of health care. While they contract the same diseases as those who are younger, there are often important differences in the way they present and how they are best managed. <ce:intra-ref id="ii0010" xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7020-7028-0.00032-9#c00032">Chapter 32</ce:intra-ref>, ‘Ageing and disease’, concentrates on the principles of managing the frailest group who suffer from multiple comorbidity and disability, and who tend to present with non-specific problems such as falls or delirium. Many older people, though, also suffer from specific single-organ pathology. ‘In Old Age’ boxes are thus included in each chapter and describe common presentations, implications of physiological changes of ageing, effects of age on investigations, problems of treatment in old age, and the benefits and risks of intervention in older people.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="s0055"><ce:section-title id="st0045"><ce:inline-figure baseline="0.0"><ce:link id="ln0030" locator="icon05-9780702070280" xlink:href="pii:B9780702070280000433/icon05-9780702070280" xlink:role="http://data.elsevier.com/vocabulary/ElsevierContentTypes/23.4" xlink:type="simple"/><ce:alt-text id="atte0030" role="short">Image 5</ce:alt-text></ce:inline-figure> In Pregnancy</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0060">Many conditions are different in the context of pregnancy, while some arise only during or shortly after pregnancy. Particular care must be taken with investigations (for example, to avoid radiation exposure to the fetus) and treatment (to avoid the use of drugs that harm the fetus). These issues are highlighted by ‘In Pregnancy’ boxes distributed throughout the book, which complement the new chapter on maternal medicine.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="s0060"><ce:section-title id="st0050"><ce:inline-figure baseline="0.0"><ce:link id="ln0035" locator="icon04-9780702070280" xlink:href="pii:B9780702070280000433/icon04-9780702070280" xlink:role="http://data.elsevier.com/vocabulary/ElsevierContentTypes/23.4" xlink:type="simple"/><ce:alt-text id="atte0035" role="short">Image 6</ce:alt-text></ce:inline-figure> In Adolescence</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0065">Although paediatric medicine is not covered in <ce:italic>Davidson's</ce:italic>, many chronic disorders begin in childhood and adult physicians often contribute to multidisciplinary teams that manage young patients ‘in transition’ between paediatric and adult health-care services. This group of patients often presents a particular challenge, due to the physiological and psychological changes that occur in adolescence and which can have a major impact on the disease and its management. Adolescents can be encouraged to take over responsibility from their parents/carers in managing their disease, but are naturally rebellious and often struggle to adhere to the impositions of chronic treatment. To highlight these issues, we have introduced a new chapter on adolescent and transition medicine to accompany the ‘In Adolescence’ boxes that appear in relevant chapters.</ce:para></ce:section></ce:section></ce:section></ce:section><ce:section id="s0065"><ce:section-title id="st0055">Terminology</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0070">The recommended International Non-proprietary Names (INNs) are used for all drugs, with the exception of adrenaline and noradrenaline. British spellings have been retained for drug classes and groups (e.g. amphetamines not amfetamines).</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="s0070"><ce:section-title id="st0060">Units of measurement</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0075">The International System of Units (SI units) is the recommended means of presentation for laboratory data and has been used throughout <ce:italic>Davidson's.</ce:italic> We recognise, though, that many laboratories around the world continue to provide data in non-SI units, so these have been included in the text for the commonly measured analytes. Both SI and non-SI units are also given in <ce:intra-ref id="ii0015" xlink:href="pii:B978-0-7020-7028-0.00035-4#c00035">Chapter 35</ce:intra-ref>, which describes the reference ranges used in Edinburgh's laboratories. It is important to appreciate that these reference ranges may vary from those used in other laboratories.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="s0075"><ce:section-title id="st0065">Finding what you are looking for</ce:section-title><ce:para id="p0080">A contents list is given on the opening page of each chapter. In addition, the book contains numerous cross-references to help readers find their way around, along with an extensive index. A list of up-to-date reviews and useful websites with links to management guidelines appears at the end of each chapter.<ce:display><ce:textbox id="b0010" role="alt7"><ce:alt-text id="atte0040" role="short">Unlabelled box</ce:alt-text><ce:textbox-head><ce:title id="tit0015">Giving us your feedback</ce:title></ce:textbox-head><ce:textbox-body><ce:sections><ce:para id="p0085">The Editors and Publisher hope that you will find this edition of <ce:italic>Davidson's</ce:italic> informative and easy to use. We would be delighted to hear from you if you have any comments or suggestions to make for future editions of the book. Please contact us by e-mail at: <ce:inter-ref id="iw0010" xlink:href="mailto:davidson.feedback@elsevier.com">davidson.feedback@elsevier.com</ce:inter-ref>. All comments received will be much appreciated and will be considered by the editorial team.</ce:para></ce:sections></ce:textbox-body></ce:textbox></ce:display></ce:para></ce:section></ce:sections></introduction>